Guide to the Lynn Randolph Papers
University of Houston Libraries
Lynn Randolph Papers
1967-2008
02/2007-015
Randolph, Lynn, 1938-
3.00 linear feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
The eleven series of Lynn Randolph Papers are housed in three boxes and contain documentation of her exemplary training and career in the visual fine arts including exhibits, shows, reviews, individual art projects, and collaborations.
Biographical Information:
Lynn Randolph is an artist, feminist, and human rights activist whose work spans the past four decades, from the 1960s to the 21st century. Reared in the refinery town of Port Arthur, Texas, she obtained a BFA from the University of Texas at Austin in 1961. After receiving her degree she moved to Houston, where she has lived and worked ever since. Randolph’s paintings have been exhibited widely in the United States and reproductions of her work have appeared in books, journals, and academic papers throughout the world.
In the late 1980s, Randolph received several important awards. In the summer of 1987 she went to Yaddo, the artists colony in Saratoga Springs, New York. In the summer of 1989 she started a year-long residence at The Bunting Institute (now the Radcliffe Institute) in Cambridge, Massachusetts.
Lynn Randolph's paintings have been in well over fifty exhibitions. Her one-person exhibitions have been scarcer, because she works slowly and meticulously. She calls her work metaphoric realism. The paintings have been predominantly figurative, until the last eight years when she started painting images of the Texas coast. Her most recent work uses birds as metaphors for angels, inspiration, and witnessing. Occasionally she is moved to address specific cultural and political injustices, as in her painting entitled "The Coronation of St. George," which was reproduced on the cover of The Nation magazine during the Republican convention in New York in 2004. Another painting depicting the administration of George W. Bush called "Scenes from Hell," was also published in the Nation as a full-page, color reproduction in 2007.
Randolph's paintings are in the permanent collection of several major museums and institutions, including The National Museum of Women in the Arts in Washington, D.C.; the Radcliffe Institute at Harvard University; the Menil Collection in Houston; the Museum of Fine Arts, Houston; the San Antonio Museum of Fine Arts and the Arizona State University Museum of Arts in Tempe.
From 1990 to 1996 Randolph engaged in a collaboration with the cultural critic Donna Haraway. This work was a dialogue of specific ideas and critiques relating to the use of technoscience at the end of the millennium and formed the images and text for Haraway’s book, "Modest_Witness@Second_Millennium.FemaleMan_Meets_OncoMouse." Many of these images have been reproduced internationally in books, journals, and academic papers. Randolph has also presented numerous lectures and conference speeches across the United States since the early 1980s.
Throughout her professional life Lynn Randolph has been involved with civil and human rights issues. When her children were young and their school was integrated, causing "white flight" from the neighborhood public school, she stayed put. She wrote lesson plans for grades one to six and trained forty volunteers to teach art to all of Poe School's students. It is now a fine arts magnet school with a paid art teacher. She was a charter member and chapter president of the Houston Women's Caucus for Art, and served as the regional vice-president for the national board. In 1988 she co-chaired the national meetings of the Women's Caucus for Art that occurred in Houston. In 1984 she and her friend Suzanne Bloom were co-organizers in Houston for Artist Call against U.S. intervention in Central America, an organization based in New York City.
In 1992 Randolph became a member of WAC, the Women's Action Coalition, also a New York group. She helped organize the group's actions in Houston during the Republican convention. WAC brought its drum corps to demonstrate during the convention, and Randolph helped WAC add more drummers from Houston. The Houston drum corps continued long after the convention. They were known as the Ilusas (deluded women) and Randolph performed with them until they disbanded in 1997.
In 1993 Lynn Randolph went to El Salvador with curator and museum director Marilyn Zeitlin to help organize an exhibition of Salvadoran artists called "Art Under Duress: El Salvador from 1980 to Present." The show was mounted at Arizona State University Museum with a catalogue and video tapes. It traveled to Houston and was shown at Lawndale Art Center where Randolph was a member of the artist board until the 1990s.
Lynn Randolph is currently an Artist-in-Residence at the M.D. Anderson Cancer Center where she works with patients and staff in the Palliative Care Unit.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Genre/Form of Material:
Articles; Brochures; Correspondence; Fliers (printed matter); Periodicals; Photographs; Typescripts
Personal Name:
Randolph, Lynn, 1938-
Topical Term:
Art -- Texas -- Houston; Artists -- Texas -- Houston; Feminism; Feminists; Women artists -- Texas -- Houston; Women's rights
Separated Materials:
Lynn Randolph Papers cataloged book collection (http://library.uh.edu/search~S11?/tLynn+Randolph+Papers./tlynn+randolph+papers/1%2C2%2C61%2CB/exact&FF=tlynn+randolph+papers&1%2C60%2C/indexsort=-)
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Scope and Contents
The eleven series of Lynn Randolph Papers are housed in three boxes and contain documentation of her exemplary training and career in the visual fine arts including exhibits, shows, reviews, individual art projects, and collaborations. The documentation of her longtime feminist and human rights activism in Houston and abroad is also an important part of the collection just as it is her life. Lynn Randolph's collaboration, both visual and literary, with Donna Haraway is represented as is her work for the Women's Action Coalition, the Women's Caucus for Art and the El Salvador Project. Collected published works by Ms. Randolph and others have been separated and cataloged to Special Collections. Also, the list of these catalogued items is found in Box 3, Folder 75.
Detailed List of Contents
- Art Exhibitions and Reviews
  - Art Exhibitions, 1984-1993 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Art Exhibitions, 1995-2007 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Art Exhibitions and Reviews, 1984-2003 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Contemporary Arts Museum Houston (CAMH) Directors
  - CAMH Information (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Linda Cathcart (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Suzanne Delehanty (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - James Harithas - Articles (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - James Harithas - Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - James Harithas - Open Letter (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Fellowships
  - Mary Ingraham Bunting Institute of Radcliffe College
    - 35th Anniversary Gala Reunion (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1990-1996 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Events (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Fellows Lists and Brief Biographies (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Fellowship Application Materials (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Harvard and Radcliffe Pamphlets (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Periodicals - Radcliffe News (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Periodicals - The Bunting Institute of Radcliffe College Newsletter (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Periodicals - The Radcliffe Quarterly (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Periodicals - Harvard University Gazette/Magazine (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Periodicals - Newspaper Articles (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Photographs and Art Cards (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Presentations (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Yaddo Artist Colony
    - 60th Anniversary (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Annual Report (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence - Addresses (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Correspondence - Yaddo Guests (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence - Personal Acquaintances (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Pamphlets (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Photographs and Postcards (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Yaddo Newsletter (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Feminist and Activist Activities
  - Artists Call Against U.S Intervention in Central America
    - Calendar of Events, Contact Sheet, Notes (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Newspaper Articles (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Photographs (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Poster & Pin (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Feminist Papers and Brochures
    - Exhibitions, 1974-1977 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Pamphlets (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Newspaper Articles (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - "Woman as Artist" (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - "Women in Authority: A Sociopsychological Analysis" (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - "A Personal View of the History of the Lesbian S/M Community and Movement in San Francisco" (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Art Libraries Society of North America 15th Annual Conference, Some Like It Hot Panel Discussion, "Louise Nevelson: Sculptor of Light and Shadows" (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - "Reconstructing Womanhood: The Emergence of the Afro-American Woman Novelist" (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - "Defining Feminism: A Comparative Historical Approach" (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Feminist Studies Journal (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - "Cultural Feminism Versus Post-Structuralism: The Identity Crisis in Feminist Theory" (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - "Reading Like a Feminist," "Éperon Strings," "Reading Like a Man" (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Haraway, Donna J.
    - "The Promises of Monsters: A Regenerative Politics for Inappropriate/d Others" (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Description of Artwork in "Modest_Witness@Second Millenium" (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - "FemaleMan©_Meets_OncoMouse™" and Manuscript (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - "Mice Into Wormholes: A Technoscience Fugue in Two Parts" (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - "Universal Donors in a Vampire Culture" (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - "A Note of a Sportswriter's Daughter: Companion Species" (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - "Modest Witness: A Painter’s Collaboration With Donna Haraway" (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Ilusas, The Women’s Drum Corps
    - Newspaper Articles (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Photographs (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Sheet Music (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Statement of Purpose, Membership List, Notes, Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Women’s Action Coalition (WAC)
    - Ads, Handouts (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Committee, Agendas, Meetings (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Contact Lists (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - Ilusas (Women’s Drum Corps & WAC Drum Corps) (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Media Release & Information (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Organizational Information (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - Newspaper Articles & References (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - Songs & Acts (Box 1, Folder 70)
    - Photographic Prints & Audio Tape (Box 1, Folder 71)
    - Clippings (Box 1, Folder 72)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Women's Caucus for Art and the Museum of Fine Arts, Houston
    - Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Museum of Fine Arts Board of Trustees - Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Museum of Fine Arts Board of Trustees - Bylaws, Membership List (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Museum of Fine Arts State of Texas File, 1913-1964 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Museum Policies - Articles (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Newspaper Articles (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Notes (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Report of the Accessions Committee Meeting, November 3, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Lawndale Art and Performance Center
  - Exhibitions and Events (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Governance Boards (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Mary Ross Taylor, Executive Director (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - New Building Project (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Organization Information (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Paintings
  The Paintings series includes 10 compact discs containing digital images of Lynn Randolph's paintings. The files can be accessed in the Special Collections Reading Room. Contact curator Vince Lee (velee@uh.edu) for more information.
  - Slides and Compact Discs, 1967-1976 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Slides and Compact Discs, 1977-1988 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Slides and Compact Discs, 1989-1991 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Slides and Compact Discs, 1992-1996 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Slides and Compact Discs, 1997-2001 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Slides and Compact Discs, 2001-2006 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Personal
  - Lynn Goode Gallery (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Resumes & The Orange Show Letter (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Bill Graham
    - Memorial Service Notes/Material (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Newspaper Articles (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Sympathy Cards/Notes (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Travel
    - Venice Biennale Trip, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Venice Biennale Trip, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Presentations
  - Beyond Political and Economic Equality (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Shape Shifting: Toward Multifaceted Re-Presentations of Women's Bodies (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Between Cultural Eras: the Effects of Post-Modern Thinking on the Modernist Concept of Regionalism (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Cyborgs, Wonder Women and Techno Angels: A Series of Spectacles (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Secular Uses of Traditional Religious Images in a Post-Modern Society (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Ways of Seeing: The Convergence of Art, Sciences and Technology (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - "Sound Science," Technology and Harm (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Projects
  - Art Education in Grade School
    - Art Activities for First through Sixth Grades, Teaching Art, Teacher's Supply List (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - "Art Vips Handbook: Guidelines for Art and Children" (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - "Differences are not Deficits," "Why Children Should Draw" (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Kinkaid School (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Notes on Teaching Art (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Poe Elementary School (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Resume on Children's Art Education (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - San Marcos High School (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - St. Stephen's Episcopal School, MacGregor Elementary School (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - "Teacher's Guide to Classroom Television" KLRN (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - ArtScan Gallery of Contemporary Art & Gallery in Motion
    - Exhibition Announcements, Newspaper Articles (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Exhibition Descriptions (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Statement of Purpose, Notes (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Carriage House Studio
    - Carriage House Studio Information (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - El Salvador Project
    - Art Under Duress - Arizona State University Exhibition Information & Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Art Under Duress - Audio Cassette & Video Tape (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Art Under Duress - Exhibition Description (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Art Under Duress - Lawndale Art and Performance Center Financial Aid Forms (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Art Under Duress - Lawndale Art & Performance Center Exhibition, Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Art Under Duress - Lawndale Art & Performance Center Exhibition Announcements, Newspaper Articles (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Central American Refugee Committee (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Cuba & Guatemala (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Diary & Notes (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Gulfton Area Community Activities (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Oscar Mackay (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Photographs (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Postcards (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Reconstruction Plan for El Salvador (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Slides (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - University of Houston Exchange Program (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Houston Art Center (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - The Discussion Group (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Research (Photographs and Notes)
  - Adam (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Adam and Stephanie (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Adelle (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Alexander (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - "An Interview with A Panhandler Named Arthur Gonzales" (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Andrea (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Anita (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Ann (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Annette (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Baldwin, Robert (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Bill (Box 3, Folder 20-21)
  - Bina (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Burke, Ronnie (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Carmen and Mirabai (Apocalypse) (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Carolyn (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Sean and Lisa (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Charmaine (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Chuy and Aztlan (The New Mestiza) (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Clouser (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Davis, Frank (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Ellis (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Emily (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Gertrude (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Grace (Cyborg) (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Grayson and Michelle (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Harrison, Peggy (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Harithas (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Heidi (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Helen (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Hilary (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Izabelle (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Jeff (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Jennifer (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Julia (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Lee, Jessie (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Lisa (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Macey (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Madonna (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Marie (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Martha (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Minatre, Steve (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Moore, Peggy (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Mother (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Nancy (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Neisen (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Dessima (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - New England Woods, Women in Woods (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - One-Eyed Man (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Pam (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Di Corcia, Joseph (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Randolph, Lynn (Box 3, Folder 61-64)
  - Ray (Lab and Mice) (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Ron (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Schwartz, Emily (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Shadows (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - She Pines in Her Bower (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Sol (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Surls (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Theresa (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Virginia (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Weather Watchers (Box 3, Folder 74)
- Published Material
  - Insight as Image... Manuscript (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - List of 59 Cataloged Items and Printed Catalog Records (Box 3, Folder 76)